Venkata Matcha

Senior Software Engineer with over 8 years of industrial experience, in India and a Master's degree in Computer Science from Old Dominion University, I have a proven track record of developing multi-faceted software applications, responsive UI that meet industry standards. I stay up-to-date with the latest design trends and best practices by exploring web.dev, dev.to and Dribble communities.

✓ vmatcooi@odu.edu

7579942295

Edison, NJ

https://mvsteja.github.io/portfolio

SKILLS

Programming Languages: JavaScript, Java, SQL, Typescript.

Web Technologies: HTML5, CSS3, React, Angular 2, Node.js, Jest, Enzyme, Ember Js.

UI Framework: Redux, Fluent UI, Material UI, Bootstrap, Highcharts, Plotly.

Backend Framework: SpringBoot, Express. Cloud Services: AWS, Google Cloud Platform.

Automation Tools: Docker, Kubernetes, Shell scripting, Jenkins.

Database Technologies: MySQL, MongoDB, Oracle.

Search and Analytics: ElasticSearch, GCP. Data Querying: Axios, QueryDSL, React Query

Task management: Confluence, JIRA. Application Monitoring: New Relic, Sentry

Design: Figma, Invision.

Version Control: Git, Bitbucket, Gitlab Agile Methodologies: Scrum, Kanban

WORK EXPERIENCE

Old Dominion University

Graduate Research Assistant Aug 2021 - May 2023

- Built end-to-end systems for ODU websites, with Front-end in Angular and React, And Backend in Node's Express JS, MySql.
- Solved the recurring dates problem in a room booking Web Interface system, ensured seamless functionality.
- Implemented ElasticSearch by importing and managing large datasets, incorporated two-factor authentication and password reset via email.
- Developed Real-Time communication application use cases such as Order updates, Chat messaging.
- Created a reusable component library for the web application used Angular Material, resulted in faster development time for new features.
- Incorporated third-party APIs, such as a payment gateway (Square) into the website, allowing for secure online payments, into the web application for data exchange and real-time updates.
- Worked with Nosql solutions like MongoDb and MongoDb Cloud.
- Tech Stack Angular 2, TypeScript, ReactJS, React Hooks, NodeJS, Express, Socket IO, MySQL, AWS EC2, Gitlab, Shell scripting, websockets, Square SDK, Docker, Kubernetes.

Map Communications Inc.

Software Engineer Intern

Jun 2022 - Aug 2022

- Built document sharing and metrics dashboard features for a Virtual Receptionist software company.
- Refactored and converted UI projects into reusable components, optimized bandwidth usage and enhanced site performance.
- Managed CI/CD pipelines, and implemented build scripts, continuous integration infrastructure, and deployment tools.
- Implemented an efficient data fetching layer used Node.js, Express.js, and React-query.
- Worked extensively with Restful APIs, implemented JWT and LDAP authentication and handled bulk operations, used packages like QueryDSL.
- Form Validations and Handled Dynamic Validations for Form using Yup.
- Utilized CSS-in-IS techniques to create a consistent and visually appealing UI.
- Ensured authentication and authorization using JWT tokens.
- Leveraged modern JavaScript features such as async/await and Promises for asynchronous coding.
- Implemented File storage, using GCP cloud. Uploaded converted byte files, from Spring APIs.
- Integrated Twilio, into an Call services app. Leveraged services like Voice Sdk, Chat, Sms.
- Written test cases with Junit and mocked external libraries using Mockito.
- Conducted pre-testing of web service calls using Swagger UI and Postman.
- Experience Dockerizing API service, and deploying to kubernetes pod through gitlab.

Tech Stack - Linux, Gitlab, Jenkins, Shell scripting, React, React Hooks, Material UI, React Native, nginx, Java, SpringBoot, Oracle DB, React query, CI/CD GitLab, kubernetes.

Freshworks

Senior Software Engineer Nov 2018 - Aug 2021

- Successfully developed and migrated data visualizations from Plotly to Highcharts.
- Implemented complex UI features such as bulk updates, bulk email, and consumption of form services.
- Participated in code reviews on Github to ensure code quality and adherence to best practices.
- Followed SDLC phases such as ideation, planning, development, testing, and production deployment. All phases were executed in an Agile 2-week sprint model.
- Collaborated with teams to slice epics into actionable user stories and resolve inter-team dependencies.
- Collaborated with peers from development, product, and project management teams to identify blockers in grooming sessions and reduce sprint planning time.
- Received mockups on Figma, Understood user flows, and developed UI based on the wireframes.
- Wrote unit tests with Jest and Enzyme, resulting in 80% code coverage. This ensured the reliability and correctness of the application.
- Defined test cases and metrics in collaboration with QA.
- Worked with CI/CD pipelines in Jenkins, and deployed packages and assets to AWS.
- Experience Dockerizing API service, and deploying to kubernetes pod through github and jenkins.
- Optimized website performance using tools like Lighthouse and resolved front-end-related issues.
- Redesigned scroll behavior using intersection observer API and other proofs-of-concept, resulting in 30% less page loading time.
- Architected Freshworks CRM Outlook Add-in using React.
- Tech Stack React, Redux, Typescript, LocalForage, Plotly, Fluent UI, Ember JS, Jest, Enzyme, Highcharts, Kubernetes, Java, Spring, AWS EC2, S3., Github, JIRA, New Relic.

Cognizant Technology Solutions

Senior Associate Aug 2013 - Nov 2018

- Implemented a MySQL database to manage user data, admin data, question banks, and past scores
- Built frontend with functionalities such as registration, take quiz, admin access, managing questions, and managing candidates, styled the application in Pearson's DLS (Design Language System).
- The UX team uploaded mockups on Invision, UI based on the feedback given by me.
- Set up route-based code-splitting of application code. Worked on improving the landing page's load speed, Reducing the time to first interactive by 30%.
- Responsible for gathering business and functional requirements (Requirement Analysis Documents), and designing and developing web applications. Followed Agile sprint model.
- Implemented Jest snapshot and unit testing, integrating pre-commit scripts.
- Tech Stack React, Redux Thunk, Redux Form, Pearson components(CSS framework), Jest, Enzyme, AngularJS, Bootstrap, On-prem Debian, Invision, Confluence, Bitbucket.

EDUCATION

Old Dominion University, cum laude

Master of Science (M.S.) - Computer Science

Aug 2021 - May 2023

Norfolk, VA

Indian Institute of Information Technology

Bachelor of Engineering (B.E.) - Electronics Engineering

Sep 2008 - May 2012

Chennai, India